Guide to the Paul Leicester Ford Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Paul Leicester Ford papers
1736-1902
1885-1902
YCAL MSS 488
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
10.35
(30 boxes) + 3 art.
The collection consists of correspondence, writings, and personal papers of the American historian and author Paul Leicester Ford. The correspondence is largely professional and documents Ford's work as an editor, historian, bibliographer, novelist and playwright. Ford's correspondents include John Kendrick Bangs, Samuel L. Clemens, Edward Everett Hale, Thomas Wentworth Higginson, Rudyard Kipling, and S. Weir Mitchell; earlier letters written to others by James Fennimore Cooper and Jared Sparks are also present. Writings include notes and research materials, most concerning colonial and Federal-period America; drafts; printed versions of published articles; scripts and music for dramatic productions; and publicity for specific works as well as about Ford generally. The novel Janice Meredith and its dramatic adaptation starring Mary Mannering are partiuclarly well represented in the collection; also present is an unfinished historical novel about Elizabeth Chudleigh, Countess of Bristol, along with contemporary printed documentation concerning her trial for bigamy. The collection also contains examples of Ford's work as an editor/printer on his home press, including his genealogy of Noah Webster; a heavily extra-illustrated copy of Websteriana containing autograph manuscript fragments of Webster's dictionary; a genealogy of Gordon L. Ford; and a pamphlet entitled "1814. New London. Pettypaug Point." Some papers documenting the historical research of Worthington C. Ford are present, as well as ephemera from Gordon L. Ford's participation in events commemorating the centenary of Washington's inauguration. The collection also includes photographs and paintings of Ford, including two miniatures; a miniature of "Janice Meredith"; photographs of his parents and siblings; and portrait paintings of Ford's ancestors Noah Webster (by Samuel F. B. Morse) and Rebecca Greenleaf Webster (by Jared Bradley Flagg).
Ford, Paul Leicester, 1865-1902
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lesta Ford Clay and Albert G. Clay, 1954-1977.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Separated Materials
Books and some other printed items received with the collection were removed for separate cataloging at the time of acquisition and can be accessed by searching the library's online catalog.
Associated Materials
Paul Leicester Ford Papers, Manuscripts and Archives Division, The New York Public Library, Astor, Lenox and Tilden Foundations.
Paul Leicester Ford (1865-1902)
American historian and novelist Paul Leicester Ford was born in Brooklyn, New York, one of eight children of lawyer, businessman, and bibliophile Gordon Lester Ford and Emily Ellsworth Fowler Ford, a poet and granddaughter of lexicographer Noah Webster. Due to chronic ill health resulting from a spinal injury in infancy, he received no formal education. He read widely in his father's extensive private library, and made use of his own printing press: at age eleven he edited and printed a genealogy of his ancestor Noah Webster, and at seventeen published a bibliography of Webster. Ford subsequently wrote and edited a large number of books and pamphlets chiefly relating to American history and bibliography, including an edition of Jefferson's writings and biographies of Washington and Franklin. In this work he frequently collaborated with his older brother, the historian Worthington C. Ford; together they published on their home press as the Historical Printing Club. Ford also wrote short fiction, plays, and novels, the most successful of which were The Honorable Peter Stirling (1894) and Janice Meredith (1899). He co-edited The Library Journal from 1890 to 1893.
Ford married Grace Kidder in 1900; they had one daughter, Lesta, who was born June 3, 1902. Paul Leicester Ford was killed by his brother Malcolm on May 8, 1902, in a dispute over family inheritance.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, writings, and personal papers of the American historian and author Paul Leicester Ford. The correspondence is largely professional and documents Ford's work as an editor, historian, bibliographer, novelist and playwright. Ford's correspondents include John Kendrick Bangs, Samuel L. Clemens, Edward Everett Hale, Thomas Wentworth Higginson, Rudyard Kipling, and S. Weir Mitchell; earlier letters written to others by James Fennimore Cooper and Jared Sparks are also present. Writings include notes and research materials, most concerning colonial and Federal-period America; drafts; printed versions of published articles; scripts and music for dramatic productions; and publicity for specific works as well as about Ford generally. The novel Janice Meredith and its dramatic adaptation starring Mary Mannering are partiuclarly well represented in the collection; also present is an unfinished historical novel about Elizabeth Chudleigh, Countess of Bristol, along with contemporary printed documentation concerning her trial for bigamy. The collection also contains examples of Ford's work as an editor/printer on his home press, including his genealogy of Noah Webster; a heavily extra-illustrated copy of Websteriana containing autograph manuscript fragments of Webster's dictionary; a genealogy of Gordon L. Ford; and a pamphlet entitled "1814. New London. Pettypaug Point." Some papers documenting the historical research of Worthington C. Ford are present, as well as ephemera from Gordon L. Ford's participation in events commemorating the centenary of Washington's inauguration. The collection also includes photographs and paintings of Ford, including two miniatures; a miniature of "Janice Meredith;" photographs of his parents and siblings; and portrait paintings of Ford's ancestors Noah Webster (by Samuel F. B. Morse) and Rebecca Greenleaf Webster (by Jared Bradley Flagg).
Arrangement
Organized into five series: Series I. Correspondence. Series II. Writings. Series III. Other Papers. Series IV. Printed Material. Series V. 1976-1977 Addition.
Authors, American -- 19th century -- Archives; Editors -- United States; Historical fiction, American; Historians -- United States; History -- Research; Incidental music -- Parts; Novelists, American; Stage adaptations; United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; United States -- History -- 1783-1815; Miniatures (paintings); Photographic prints; Oil paintings (visual works); Historians; Editors; Novelists; Bangs, John Kendrick, 1862-1922; Bristol, Elizabeth Chudleigh, Countess of, 1720-1788; Clemens, Samuel Langhorne, 1835-1910; Cooper, James Fenimore, 1789-1851; Ford family; Ford, Emily Ellsworth Fowler, 1826-1893; Ford, Gordon Lester, 1823-1891; Ford, Paul Leicester, 1865-1902; Ford, Worthington Chauncey, 1858-1941; Flagg, Jared B. (Jared Bradley), 1820-1899; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790; Hale, Edward Everett, 1822-1909; Higginson, Thomas Wentworth, 1823-1911; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826; Kipling, Rudyard, 1865-1936; Mannering, Mary, 1876-1953 -- Portraits; Mitchell, S. Weir (Silas Weir), 1829-1914; Morse, Samuel Finley Breese, 1791-1872; Sparks, Jared, 1789-1866; Washington, George, 1732-1799; Webster, Noah, 1758-1843; Webster, Noah, 1758-1843 -- Portraits; Webster, Rebecca Greenleaf, 1766-1847 -- Portraits; Historical Printing Club (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); Library Journal (Firm)
- Correspondence, circa 1885-1902; Series I; 4; 1.67 linear_feet
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains correspondence documenting Paul Leicester Ford's work as an editor, historian, bibliographer, novelist and playwright.
  - "A" general (Box 1)
  - Albert, Scott Co. (Box 1)
  - Adams, Chas. F. (Box 1)
  - American Antiquarian Society (Box 1)
  - American Historical Review (Box 1)
  - American Jewish Historical Society (Box 1)
  - American Library Association (Box 1)
  - American Philosophical Society (Box 1)
  - Anderson, John (Box 1)
  - D. Appleton Company (Box 1)
  - The Atlantic Monthly (Box 1)
  - Avery, Sam P. (Box 1)
  - "B" general (Box 1)
  - Bacheller, Irving (Box 1)
  - Bangs, John Kendrick (Box 1)
  - Bement, Clarence S. (Box 1)
  - Benjamin, Walter R. (Box 1)
  - Bigelow, John (Box 1)
  - Book Lovers Library (Box 1)
  - Boston Public Library (Box 1)
  - Bowen, Clarence Winthrop (Box 1)
  - Bryce, James (Box 1)
  - "C" general (Box 1)
  - Century Magazine (Box 1)
  - Chase, J. Eastman (Box 1)
  - Clayton, Joseph C. (Box 1)
  - Clemens, Samuel Langhorne (Box 1)
  - Collier's Weekly (Box 1)
  - Columbia University (Box 1)
  - Archibald Constable Company (Box 1)
  - Conway, Moncure Daniel (Box 1)
  - Cooper, James Fenimore (Box 1)
  - Cosmopolitan Magazine (Box 1)
  - Criterion Theatre (Box 1)
  - Curtis Cameron Publishers (Box 1)
  - "D" general (Box 1)
  - De Forest, Robert W. (Box 1)
  - The De Vinne Press (Box 1)
  - Dodd, Mead Company, 2 (Box 1)
  - Doubleday, Page Company (Box 1)
  - Dowling, Mildred T. (Box 1)
  - The Dunlap Society (Box 2)
  - E. P. Dutton Company (Box 2)
  - Dwight, Theodore F. (Box 2)
  - "E" general (Box 2)
  - Eames, Wilberforce (Box 2)
  - Egle, William H. (Box 2)
  - A. W. Elson Co. (Box 2)
  - "F" general (Box 2)
  - Fitch, Clyde (Box 2)
  - Ford, Worthington C. (Box 2)
  - Frohman, Charles (Box 2)
  - "G" general (Box 2)
  - Gaine, Hugh (Box 2)
  - Garland, Hamlin (Box 2)
  - George, Henry (Box 2)
  - Gibson, Charles Dana (Box 2)
  - Gillette, William (Box 2)
  - Gilliss Brothers Printers (Box 2)
  - Gosse, Edmund (Box 2)
  - "H" general (Box 2)
  - Hale, Edward Everett (Box 2)
  - Hare, Augustus J. C. (Augustus John Cuthbert) (Box 2)
  - Harper and Brothers (Box 2)
  - Hart, Albert B. (Box 2)
  - Harvard University Library (Box 2)
  - Havemeyer, W.F. (Box 2)
  - Higginson, Thomas Wentworth (Box 2)
  - Hildeburn, Charles R. (Box 2)
  - Henry Holt Company (Box 2)
  - Houghton, Mifflin and Company (Box 2)
  - "I" general (Box 2)
  - "J" general (Box 2)
  - Jay, William (Box 2)
  - "K" general (Box 2)
  - Kipling, Rudyard (Box 2)
  - Kite, Mary M. (Box 2)
  - "L" general (Box 3)
  - La Farge, John (Box 3)
  - Library of Congress (Box 3)
  - J. B. Lippincott Company (Box 3)
  - Little, Brown and Company (Box 3)
  - Lodge, Henry Cabot (Box 3)
  - Longmans, Green Co. (Box 3)
  - "M" general (Box 3)
  - The Macmillan Company (Box 3)
  - S. S. McClure, Limited (Box 3)
  - Manchester, L. C. (Box 3)
  - Mansfield, Richard (Box 3)
  - Marbury, Elizabeth (Box 3)
  - Mason, Alfred Bishop (Box 3)
  - Massachusetts Historical Society (Box 3)
  - Matthews, Brander (Box 3)
  - Mitchell, S. Weir (Silas Weir) (Box 3)
  - "N" general (Box 3)
  - The Nation (Box 3)
  - New England Magazine (Box 3)
  - New Hampshire State Library (Box 3)
  - New York Library Club (Box 3)
  - New York Public Library (Box 3)
  - New York Tribune (Box 3)
  - Nordhoff, Charles (Box 3)
  - "O" general (Box 3)
  - "P" general (Box 3)
  - Parkman, Francis (Box 3)
  - Pennsylvania Historical Society (Box 3)
  - Pine, John B. (Box 3)
  - Porter, H. M. (Box 3)
  - Prince Society (Box 3)
  - Publishers Weekly (Box 3)
  - G. P. Putnam's Sons (Box 3)
  - Pyle, Howard (Box 3)
  - "R" general (Box 3)
  - "S" general (Box 4)
  - Sabin, J. F. (Box 4)
  - Sachse, Julius F. (Box 4)
  - Sampson Low Marston Company (Box 4)
  - Charles Scribner's Sons (Box 4)
  - Shear, T. Leslie (Box 4)
  - Skeel, Roswell (Box 4)
  - Sparks, Jared (Box 4)
  - Stedman, Arthur (Box 4)
  - Stevens, Benjamin Franklin (Box 4)
  - Stokes, Frederick A. (Box 4)
  - Sumner, William Graham (Box 4)
  - The Sun, New York (Box 4)
  - "T" general (Box 4)
  - Taylor, Douglas (Box 4)
  - Thomas, Augustus (Box 4)
  - The Tree Planting and Fountain Society of Brooklyn, 2 (Box 4)
  - Tuck, Edward (Box 4)
  - The Typothetæ (Box 4)
  - "U" general (Box 4)
  - "V" general (Box 4)
  - Van Sanford, Anna Townsend (Box 4)
  - Vanderbilt, George (Box 4)
  - Veblen, Thorstein (Box 4)
  - Vedder, Elihu (Box 4)
  - "W" general (Box 4)
  - Watt, A. P. (Box 4)
  - Washington, Lawrence (Box 4)
  - Weber, Oswald, Jr. (Box 4)
  - Charles L. Webster Co. Publishers (Box 4)
  - Wendell, Evert Jansen (Box 4)
  - Winsor, Justin (Box 4)
  - Woodward, Charles L. (Box 4)
  - Woolsey, Arixene Southgate (Box 4)
  - "Y" general (Box 4)
  - Yale University Library (Box 4)
  - "Z" general (Box 4)
  - Unidentified (Box 4)
- Writings, circa 1885-1902; Series II; 12; 4.46 linear_feet
  Organized into two subseries: Historical Writings and Fiction.
  Historical writings include drafts and printed versions of essays, book reviews, letters to the editor, and research notes. Of particular interest is copy number 1 of 6 of Ford's Websteriana, printed on his own press and extra-illustrated with fragments of a draft of Webster's dictionary in Webster's hand. Fictional writings include drafts of novels, plays, and shorter works.
  - Historical Writings
    Arranged alphabetically by title and/or subject.
    - Abstract of G. Morris's plan of American finance (Box 5)
    - Adoption of the Pennsylvania Constitution of 1776 (Box 5)
    - The American Catalogue - review (Box 5)
    - "The American History Novel" (Box 5)
      General
      Published in The Atlantic, December 1897
    - American history paper (Box 5)
    - "The Association of the First Congress" (Box 5)
      Published in Political Science Quarterly, December 1891
    - "In re Bache and Duane" (Box 5)
      Published in The Nation, 1890
    - "The Beginnings of American Dramatic Literature" (Box 5)
    - Benedict Arnold (Box 5)
    - Letter on Braddock's defeat (Box 5)
      Published in The Nation, July 30, 1896
    - "Calendar of State Papers" - review (Box 5)
      Published in The Nation, July 9, 1896; and New York Evening Post, July 27, 1896
    - "Catalogue of Americana," Charles F. Libbie co. (sale of Friday December 14, 1888) (Box 5)
    - William Chamberlain controversy (Box 5)
      Letter to The Nation
    - "The Charities Review" (Box 5)
    - Chase-Greeley letters (Box 5)
    - Chaunciana - A Charles Chauncey bibliography (Box 5)
    - Charles Chauncey and Noah Webster notes (Box 5)
    - Checklist of American magazines (Box 5)
    - "Cobbett's Censor" (Box 5)
    - Columbia University - Department of Sociology (Box 5)
    - Review of Connecticut; a study of a commonwealth-democracy by Alexander Johnston (Box 6)
      Published in Political Science Quarterly, September 1887
    - "The Conway Cabal", 1895 May (Box 6)
    - "J. Fenimore Cooper" (Box 6)
    - "Dawson's Federalist" (Box 6)
    - "Detail" (Box 6)
    - "Direct taxes in 1787-1894" (Box 6)
      Published in The New York Times, May 1, 1895
    - Reviews: Doubleday Page Company and Collier's Weekly (Box 6)
    - "A list of Early American imprints...", review (Box 6)
    - The Federalist (Box 6)
    - "The Financial Literature of the United States, 1776-1789" (Box 6)
    - The First American Play (Box 6)
    - Paul Leicester Ford biography (Box 6)
    - "Franklin and Snakes" (Box 6)
      Letter to The Nation, September 1, 1898
    - "Franklin's Poor Richard" (Box 6)
    - "The many sides of Franklin" (Box 6)
    - "A new portrait of Franklin" (Box 6)
    - "A study of Franklin" (Box 6)
    - "Who was the mother of Franklin's son" (Box 6)
    - Philip Freneau bibliography (Box 6)
    - Freneau's "National Gazette" (Box 6)
    - "The Genesis of the Monroe Doctrine" (Box 6)
      Published in The New York Times, January 22, 1896
    - "Giles' Treasury Resolution" (Box 6)
    - Graham Library (Box 6)
    - Samuel A. Green imprints (Box 6)
    - Hamilton's "Assumption" (Box 6)
    - Alexander Hamilton archive notes (Box 6)
    - Review of Charles Swift Riché Hildeburn's The Charlemagne Tower collection of American colonial laws (Box 6)
    - Review of Charles Swift Riché Hildeburn's Sketches of Printers and Printing in Colonial New York (Box 6)
    - "Lord Howe's Commission to Pacify the Colonies" (Box 6)
    - "History of the Continental Congress" (Box 7)
    - Review of History of the Horn-Book by Andrew W. Tuer (Box 7)
      Published in The Nation, August 13, 1896
    - "How the Revolution was Fought" (Box 7)
    - Review of Hugh Wynne, Free Quaker, sometime brevet lieutenant-colonel on the staff of His Excellency General Washington by S. Weir Mitchell (Box 7)
    - "Ideals of the Republic" (Box 7)
    - "An Index to Biographies and Portraits" (Box 7)
    - "List of some briefs in appeals cases" (Box 7)
    - "The Inauguration of our Government" (Box 7)
      Published in Harper's Weekly, 1889
    - "Israel Putnam" (Box 7)
      Published in The Independent, June 21, 1888
    - "Jefferson's Drafts of the Kentucky Revolution" (Box 7)
      Published in The Nation, February 20, 1896
    - "Jefferson in France;" letter to The Nation, 1895 (Box 7)
    - "Jefferson on Novels" (Box 7)
    - "Jefferson's Notes on Virginia" (Box 7)
    - "Elson's Jefferson" (Box 7)
    - "Thomas Jefferson in Undress" (Box 7)
      Published in Scribner's Magazine, October 1892
    - "Lafayette in the American Review" (Box 7)
      Published in The Atlantic, July 1896
    - "Letters of William Lee" (Box 7)
    - "The Life and Correspondence of Rufus King" (Box 7)
    - "The Life of Arthur Lee" (Box 7)
    - List of members of the Federal Convention (Box 7)
    - "A List of the Library of Congress Catalogues" (Box 7)
    - "Long Island" (Box 7)
    - "Love Letters of our Forefathers" (Box 7)
    - "A Modern Babel" (Box 7)
    - Review of Morse's Franklin (Box 7)
    - "The New Lewis and Clark" (Box 7)
    - Notes on Adam Smith's Wealth of Nations (Box 7)
    - Notes on Connecticut law and polity (Box 7)
    - Notes on rare books (Box 8)
    - "Notes taken from Steven's facsimiles" (Box 8)
    - "The Origin, Purpose, and Result of the Harrisburg Convention" (Box 8)
    - Pelham-Copley correspondence (Box 8)
    - Pennsylvania's first constitution (Box 8)
    - "The Personality of a Library" (Box 8)
    - "Pickney's Draft of a Constitution" (Box 8)
      Published in The Nation, June 13, 1895
    - "Portrait of James Wolfe" (Box 8)
    - "Private libraries" (Box 8)
    - "A Question in Literary Ethics" (Box 8)
      Published in Literary World, December 25, 1897; and Critic, January 8, 1898
    - "Specialization of New York Libraries" (Box 8)
      Published in Library Journal, 1890
    - Syllabus of sources of American history (Box 8)
    - The Tilden Library (Box 8)
    - Trust companies (Box 8)
    - Venezuelan maps - correspondence (Box 8)
    - George Washington -- draft of article (Box 8)
    - The true George Washington--blurb (Box 8)
    - Washington and the theatre, 2 (Box 8)
    - Websteriana: a catalogue of books by Noah Webster, collated from the library of Gordon L. Ford. (Brooklyn, N.Y., 1882) (Box 8)
      Compiled by Paul Leicester Ford and Emily Ellsworth Ford. Number 1 of 6 copies; extra-illustrated with manuscripts (including autograph fragments of Webster's dictionary), engravings, and other printed material.
  - Fiction
    Arranged alphabetically by title.
    - "Beauty and the Beast" (Box 9)
    - "A Checkered Love Affair" (Box 9)
    - "Chris Morton's Patriotism" (Box 9)
    - "Cupid's Insurrection" (Box 9)
    - The Great K A Train-Robbery, cover illustration (Box 9)
    - "Honors Are Easy"
      - Drafts, 4 (Box 9)
      - Cue scripts, 2 (Box 9)
      - Cue scripts (continued), 1 (Box 10)
    - "The Cortelyou Feud" (Box 10)
    - "His Version Of It" (Box 10)
    - The Honorable Peter Sterling, 2 (Box 10)
    - "A House Party - 'A Family Tradition'" (Box 10)
    - Janice Meredith
      - Autograph drafts, 8 (Box 11)
      - Autograph and typescript drafts, corrected, 2 (Box 12)
      - Typescript drafts, 4 (Box 12)
      - Page proofs (Box 13)
      - Stage adaptation
        - Autograph manuscript (Box 12)
        - Act I typescript (Box 12)
        - Act II typescript (Box 12)
        - Partial typescript draft, 2 (Box 12)
      - Setting typescript, 3 (Box 14)
      - Dedication (Box 14)
      - Scenario (Box 14)
      - Miscellaneous notes (Box 14)
      - Galley proofs (Box 14)
    - "Sauce for the Goose" (Box 14)
    - "Sewing Society" (Box 14)
    - "Tattle-Tales", 2 (Box 14)
    - "Wanted - A Chaperon" (Box 15)
    - "Wanted - A Matchmaker", 2 (Box 15)
    - "A Warning To Lovers" (Box 15)
    - "The Western Story" (Box 15)
    - Unfinished, untitled novel, 7 (Box 16)
      Based on the life of Elizabeth Chudleigh, Countess of Bristol, also known as Duchess of Kingston
- Other Papers, 1878-1902; Series III; 6; 1.92 linear_feet
  Organized into three subseries: Clippings, Research Files, and Visual Materials.
  Other papers consist of clippings, research files, and visual material. Clippings include reviews, publicity materials, and articles documenting Ford's personal life. Research files document Ford's interest in American financial history and Worthington C. Ford's research concerning George Washington, and also include a genealogy of the Ford family, likely printed and extra-illustrated by Ford. The series also includes photographs and drawings of Ford, his family, and his homes, as well as dramatic productions of his works.
  - Clippings
    - "The Bibliographer", 1901-1902 (Box 17)
    - The Great K A Train-Robbery (Box 17)
    - The Honorable Peter Sterling, 1896-1907 (Box 17)
    - "Honors Are Easy", 1896, undated (Box 17)
    - "A House Party", 1901-1902, undated (Box 17)
    - Janice Meredith, 1900; 6 (Box 17)
    - Janice Meredith (continued), 1901-1902, undated; 3 (Box 18)
    - "The Many Sided Franklin", 1898-1901, undated (Box 18)
    - "The New England Primer", 1896-1900 (Box 18)
    - "Wanted - A Matchmaker", 1900-1902 (Box 18)
    - Miscellaneous articles about Ford's work, 1890-1902, undated (Box 18)
    - Miscellaneous articles about Paul Leicester Ford, 1888-1902, undated; 6 (Box 18)
    - Miscellaneous articles about Paul Leicester Ford (continued), 1888-1902, undated; 2 (Box 19)
    - Articles written by Paul Leicester Ford, 1888-1902, undated (Box 19)
    - Engagement to Grace Kidder, 1900, undated (Box 19)
    - Clippings collected by Paul Leicester Ford (Box 19)
    - Miscellaneous clippings (Box 20)
  - Research files
    - Family Record of Gordon Lester Ford, [1878]; 2 (Box 20)
      Printed, unbound, extra-illustrated with manusripts, photographs
    - General research files, 3 (Box 20)
    - Alexander Hamilton's treasury reports (Box 20)
    - Treasury Department research
      - "A 76 Courtship" (Box 20)
      - Boucher settlement (Box 20)
      - Dickinson and the Pennsylvania constitution (Box 20)
      - The Federalist (Box 20)
      - Virginia constitution (Box 20)
      - Virginia election (Box 20)
    - Worthington C. Ford research files, 6 (Box 20)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 20)
  - Visual Material
    - Photographs of Paul Leicester Ford, 2 (Box 21)
    - Production photographs of Janice Meredith, 3 (Box 21)
      Includes images of actress Mary Mannering in the title role
    - Ford residences (Box 21)
    - Ford residences (Box 22)
    - Ford residence, floor plans (Box 22)
    - "Janice Meredith," images of Mary Mannering and reproductions of O'Ryan miniature (Box 22)
    - Miscellaneous photographs, drawings, and ephemera (Box 22)
      Includes two photographs of Paul Leicester Ford and one of Gordon L. Ford
- Printed Material, 1736-1902; Series IV; 2; 0.63 linear_feet
  Arranged alphabetically by title with some unsorted material filed at the end of the series.
  The series contains printed material documenting Ford's research interests, writings, and editorship of Library Journal.
  - "American Foundation History" (Box 23)
  - "Catalog of the Loan Exhibition of Historical Portraits and Relics", 1889 (Box 23)
    Washington inauguration centennial